It's about 10 minutes, let's begin.
We're doing a backwards
[music].
This meditation includes two
meditations. Okay, let's begin. Let's start
with 20 breaths.
I'd like to offer you the
Illuminaries, the seven
preparatory exercises.
So, choose a piece of food
and fresh juice. Do you want
some
juice or a piece of red or white,
whatever comes
[music]?
Brought home or here to this
temple.
Thank him.
Try to change yourself to how they
look,
and then try to imagine where they
bought it, maybe from a store.
And imagine those people
working there,
putting the food on the displays. They
work all day. It's hard work.
Someone made the money.
Someone made the paper of money.
No one made the plastic of the
credit card. Someone
developed online banking.
Hundreds of people are involved in it.
Someone bought the vegetables and fruit from
the field.
I did that in college. I
loaded the food into the truck,
carried it into the truck, and it's really
hard work.
Someone
selected that fruit and vegetables and packed them in the crates. It's
really hard work. Did they do that in
the fields?  Watered,
fertilized, and
harvested, the fields also cleared of
weeds,
they are already a part of our
bodies, time, so
they have a right to a part of
our time, they
have a right to what
we do with our bodies, a part of it,
they have a right to
the pages, to thank it, and the thought of thanking it,
and that is the thought
that they have a right to a
part of our work,
also has a history,
and that is the second meditation
I want to do for you today,
the idea of
thinking about it,
the idea that other people have the
same right to a part of my time,
how did this idea begin,
what is the line for this idea,
I heard it in,
then I want you to mentally go back
the thoughts, the trains of thought that introduce you
to this point
today, the possibility that other
people already have a share, a right to
your time,
that they, a day, if we respect the idea
that everyone,
that everyone in this space, in this world,
has fundamental rights,
and therefore
people fundamentally already have a right
to your time, because they have
fed me, because they have given you their time,
and they have given you your clothes,
and they have made your house,
and where does this
idea come from for the very first time, with
this  Equality,
why am I talking about this? Because I heard about it.
I had a thought. I thought
I'd like to hear more about it.
What did you think about?
I considered what improvements
I could make. I heard about this, about this honor, about
Lamarim.
Where does this come from? I think
when I was in college, I heard about
Buddhism. I did
n't study it, but I heard about it,
and I thought about
what had happened before
I
went to college.
This comes from my family.
When I think about what
my mother and father
said about going to
college, during
my high school years,
I thought about history and the
rest of the world.
And in elementary school,
I remember going to my first
class,
and I remember how I felt
and how interested
but also respectful I was. I
remember
the first few days before I was allowed to go
to school for the first time.
I was with my mother, with
my father, with my family. I
remember things we
talked about,
thoughts I had.
I remember a day in my
flu  When I
touched a toy and how soft it
was, and I
thought about soft ice cream, and what I want you to do is do
two different kinds of
meditation. One is with a
physical object. Take something you
ate that made you feel anxious, something
you drank, a house
you just left, and go back
to all the people involved in
making those materials, all the
people who contributed their knowledge
to build houses, and thank them.
Go back and thank them.
Gratitude is a really healthy
and happy activity that creates happiness.
And in the second meditation
you want to do today,
choose one of you who has also taken a step. There is a
prime time, a priority time, and one
that is mid-morning.
There, look back in your
thoughts and see how far back you
can go.
[Music]
And you can go back
to the days when you were a baby and when
you were just born.
It is possible to go back,
and maybe you can break through.
Maybe you can
go to the spaces where you
found yourself before that birth. It is
possible
for your thoughts to flow.
All the time you were conscious, you had a
recording in  Your mind of past
lives, you just have to try to enter them,
so why are we working on going back
with your food,
your clothes, your house, and
being grateful?
Because
with an even deeper meditation,
your mind is fresh, you go back into
your thoughts step by step by
step, and this is a very, very deep
meditation, and it has a great influence
on
seeing directly in the long term.
This is the practice of making your thoughts go back,
and as you get better, it
's true, on the first day it will be a
little difficult, but after a
week
you will be much, much better at it,
and this has a lot of power to
have the ability to
see most things directly.
So, two different types of
retrospective meditation: one of a
fruit, or a car, or a
house, and the other
is a meditation
where you trace your thoughts back and
you see which thought came before the
last thought.
[Music]
You can trace every thought back;
you can remember, "Oh, I had
this thought ten years ago,
and twelve years before that." And if you
practice this,
you can
see where you were before this life, and
it's a lot of fun, and above all,
you remember all those
thoughts you already had there. Okay, guys.
Take a drink, lie down,
stretch, have a sip,
okay? See you tomorrow
at 3 PM Berlin time.
It's fun being with you all.
Thank you so much, I see your
smiling faces.
Thank you to Franziska and all the
staff.
Thank you
to the translators. See you tomorrow
at 6 AM.